Guide to the Mary Welsh Hemingway Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Welsh Hemingway papers
1892-1977
YCAL MSS 392
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.5
(10 boxes)
The Mary Welsh Hemingway Papers document the life and career of the journalist Mary Welsh Hemingway, and include correspondence, writings, and personal papers. The correspondence includes letters to Mary and Ernest Hemingway from a variety of correspondents, both family and professional; copies of outgoing letters written by Ernest Hemingway; correspondence related to Mary Hemingway's involvement with the Overseas Press Club of America; and holiday cards and notes written to her mother, Adeline Welsh. The bulk of the writings is comprised of typescript drafts of Mary Hemingway's autobiography How it Was. Writings related to her father, Thomas J. Welsh, her travels, and other topics are also present. Personal and other papers include clippings related to Mary Hemingway's travels and public appearances, and to memorials for Ernest Hemingway; financial documents; photographs; and ephemera. They also contain papers of Mary Hemingway's father, Thomas J. Welsh, including a typescript autobiography, correspondence, and other family papers.
Hemingway, Mary Welsh, 1908-1986
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Library Associates Endowment Fund, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Mary Welsh Hemingway (1908-1986)
Mary Welsh Hemingway, journalist and fourth wife of the author Ernest Hemingway, was born on April 5, 1908, in Walker, Minnesota, the daughter of Thomas James Welsh, a lumberman, and Adeline Beehler Welsh. She studied journalism at Northwestern University, and edited The American Florist before joining the staff of The Chicago Daily News in 1932. In 1937 she moved to London to write for The Daily Express, and beginning in 1940 she covered World War II in Europe for Time and Life magazines. Throughout her first two marriages, to Lawrence Cook and to Australian journalist Noel Monks, she used the name Mary Welsh professionally.
Mary Welsh met Hemingway in London in 1944, and they were married two years later in Havana, Cuba. During their fifteen years together, Mary Hemingway continued to work as a free-lance journalist but also supported her husband's writing, answering correspondence and typing his manuscripts. The couple kept homes in Idaho and Cuba, and travelled widely. Following Hemingway's suicide in 1961, she served as his literary executor and saw to press several posthumous works, including A Moveable Feast, established the Ernest Hemingway Foundation to support young writers, and arranged for the donation of his papers to the Kennedy Presidential Library. In 1976 she published her autobiography, How it Was, which focuses chiefly on her time with Ernest Hemingway.
In her later years Mary Hemingway lived in New York, where she died on November 26, 1986.
Sources include: The New York Times, 28 November 1986. Contemporary Authors Online, accessed via Gale Literary Database, 10 June 2011.
Scope and Contents
The Mary Welsh Hemingway Papers document the life and career of the journalist Mary Welsh Hemingway, and include correspondence, writings, and personal papers. The correspondence includes letters to Mary and Ernest Hemingway from a variety of correspondents, both family and professional; copies of outgoing letters written by Ernest Hemingway; correspondence related to Mary Hemingway's involvement with the Overseas Press Club of America; and holiday cards and notes written to her mother, Adeline Welsh. The bulk of the writings is comprised of typescript drafts of Mary Hemingway's autobiography How it Was. Writings related to her father, Thomas J. Welsh, her travels, and other topics are also present. Personal and other papers include clippings related to Mary Hemingway's travels and public appearances, and to memorials for Ernest Hemingway; financial documents; photographs; and ephemera. They also contain papers of Mary Hemingway's father, Thomas J. Welsh, including a typescript autobiography, correspondence, and other family papers.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1938-1976. II. Writings, 1940-1977. III. Personal and Other Papers, 1892-1972.
Authors, American -- 20th Century; Journalists -- United States -- Archives; Journalists; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Hemingway, Mary Welsh, 1908-1986; Welsh, Adeline Beehler, d. 1957; Welsh, Thomas James, 1870-1955; Overseas Press Club of America
- Correspondence, 1938-1976; Series I; 17
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged in rough chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the correspondence was removed from binders labelled A-F. Correspondence from the binders consists of letters to Mary and Ernest Hemingway from a variety of correspondents, both family and professional. The binder files include some outgoing letters by Mary Hemingway. Other correspondence includes holiday cards and notes to Hemingway's mother, Adeline Welsh; copies of letters by Ernest Hemingway; and correspondence related to Mary Hemingway's involvement with the Overseas Press Club of America.
  - Binders, 1938-1972
    - Binder A, 1949-1961 (Box 1)
    - Binder B, 1942-1957; 3 (Box 1)
    - Binder C, 1958-1972; 2 (Box 1)
    - Binder D (Box 1)
    - Binder E, 1939-1970 (Box 1)
    - Binder F, 1938-1945 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1976 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Adeline Welsh, 1950s (Box 1)
  - Copies of Ernest Hemingway correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Junk mail, circa 1965 (Box 1)
  - Letters, etc. (Box 1)
  - Overseas Press Club of America, 1972-1973; 2 (Box 1)
- Writings, circa 1940-1977; Series II; 7; (7 boxes)
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  The bulk of the writings is comprised of typescripts drafts of Mary Welsh Hemingway's autobiography How it Was. The series also includes Mary Hemingway's writings related to her father, Thomas J. Welsh; her travels; and other topics.
  - "A House is Never Finished", 2 (Box 1)
  - "A House is Never Finished" 86-162 (Box 1)
  - "A House is Never Finished" 161 page TS part I and III (Box 1)
  - "Abridged Report" draft p. 1-62 only (Box 1)
  - "An Abridged Report Part II", 2 (Box 1)
  - "An Abridged Report Part II" (continued), 2 (Box 2)
  - Binders
    - Binder G: Typed notes, 1943-1951 (Box 2)
    - Binder H: notes and essays, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Binder I: notes and essays, 1960 (Box 2)
  - How It Was
    - "How it Was", 7 (Box 2)
    - "How it Was" VII, 3 (Box 2)
    - "How it Was" VIII, 3 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 15 and 16 various (Box 3)
    - Chapters 26-32 various (Box 3)
    - Draft X fragments, 12 (Box 3)
    - Draft X pp. 0276-0400 (Box 3)
    - Draft X pp. 0401-0550 (Box 3)
    - Draft X pp. 0558-0667 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 740-0901 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 0936-1057 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1058-1200 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1201-1353 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1354-1540 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1541-1563 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1564-1884 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1885-1937 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp.0276-0550 (Alternate) (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1208-1268 (Alternate) with 1977 Knopf Letter, undated; 1977 (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp.1354-1474 (Alternate) (Box 4)
    - Draft X pp. 1516-1660 (Alternate) (Box 4)
    - Draft X 1843-1937 (Alternate) (Box 4)
    - East Africa Journal 1953, 2 (Box 4)
    - "House overpraised" II-13 to 92 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous drafts, early (16.61-6__) (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous drafts, early, 2 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 5)
    - "My Father in Minnesota" - Early Notes and drafts (Box 5)
    - "Part IV - Combined Operations" (Box 5)
    - "Part V: Cuba Bella" (Box 5)
    - Parts XVIII-XXII drafts (Box 5)
    - Parts XXIX-XXXVI drafts (Box 5)
    - Proofs pp. 1-200 (Box 5)
    - Proofs pp. 201-400 (Box 5)
    - Proofs pp. 401-537 and index (Box 5)
    - "Resume" draft 1-150 (Box 5)
    - "Resume" draft 151-300 (Box 5)
    - "Resume" draft 301-450 (Box 5)
    - "Resume" draft 451-600 (Box 5)
    - "Resume" draft 601-750 (Box 6)
    - "Resume" draft 751-900 (Box 6)
    - "Resume" draft 901-986 (Box 6)
    - "Revised Stuff" parts II and XXVII, 1975 August (Box 6)
    - Section V, 3 (Box 6)
    - Section VI, 3 (Box 6)
    - Setting copy III, 3 (Box 6)
    - Settings copy IV, 3 (Box 6)
    - Setting copy pp. 1-150 (Box 7)
    - Setting copy pp. 151-300 (Box 7)
    - Setting copy pp. 301-450 (Box 7)
    - Setting copy pp. 451-600 (Box 7)
    - Setting copy pp.601-750 (Box 7)
    - Setting copy pp. 751-890 (end) (Box 7)
    - "Under Weigh", pp. 10-23 (Box 7)
    - Various early drafts, 3 (Box 7)
  - Manuscript (Box 7)
  - Notes
    - Notes (Box 7)
    - Notes on WWII, E.H.>Mary H., 1944 (Box 7)
    - Notes - Spain, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Scratch/Notes (Box 7)
    - USSR Notes, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Published (Box 7)
- Personal and Other Papers, 1892-1972; Series III; 3; (3 boxes)
  Series III is arranged alphabetically by file title.
  Personal and other papers include clippings related to Mary Welsh Hemingway's travels, public appearances, and news items related to memorials for Ernest Hemingway; financial documents; photographs; and ephemera. They also contain papers of Thomas J. Welsh, including a typescript autobiography, correspondence, and other family papers.
  - Address Cards (Box 8)
  - Africa Trip, clippings and souvenirs, 1962 (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Clippings about Mary Hemingway (Box 8)
  - Clippings - Spain, 1968 Mar-Apr, Jul (Box 8)
  - Clippings, Cuba, 1953-1960 (Box 8)
  - Clippings about others (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1961-1965 (Box 8)
  - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Ephemera (Box 8)
    Related Archival Materials note
    Also stored in: Box 10 Oversize.
  - Financial Documents 1970s, 2 (Box 8)
  - Financial bank documents (Box 8)
  - High School Reunion, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera (Box 8)
  - Mixed Clippings (Box 8)
  - Newspapers and clippings, 2 (Box 8)
  - Overseas Press Club, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Photographs (6) (Box 8)
  - T. J. Welsh papers (Box 9)
  - T. J. Welsh autobiography typescript, 4 (Box 9)
  - Thomas J. Welsh family papers, 1892-1955 (Box 9)
  - Thomas J. Welsh family papers, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Travel ephemera, New Zealand, 2 (Box 9)
  - Green Island, Australia, 1965 (Box 9)
  - Travel Souvenirs; Green Island, Little Dix Boy, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
  - USSR Tour (Box 9)
  - Ephemera (photograph of cheetah, signed by Chuck Ennis), 1971 (Box 10 Oversize)